Guide to the Albert Dewey Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Albert Dewey Papers
1898-1958
RG 161
Yale University Divinity School Library
1.5
(3 boxes)
Detailed correspondence, writings, collected material, diaries, and photographs document the life and work of Albert Dewey and his family in Turkey. Albert Dewey was an American medical missionary serving under the American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions in Gaziantep (Aintab), Turkey from 1919 to 1959.
Dewey, Albert
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Biographical / Historical
Albert Dewey was educated at the University of Denver (B.A. 1913, M.A. 1915, M.D. 1917). He did graduate work at the University of Pennsylvania and in Vienna. In 1941 he was elected a Fellow of the American College of Physicians. He was in the U.S. Army during World War I and saw service in London and France. With his wife, Elsie Greene Dewey, he sailed to the Near East as a missionary of the American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions in 1919 for work in Talas and Merzifon. He worked for six years under Near East Relief in Turkey, Greece, Syria, and the Caucasus. He took charge of the Azariah Smith Memorial Hospital in Gaziantep, Turkey in 1929. Albert and Elsie Dewey had five children. Elsie died in 1940 and Albert married Dora Shank, a nursing supervisor in Turkey, in 1942. The Deweys retired from their work in 1959.
Scope and Contents
Detailed correspondence to Dewey's parents, sibling, and children provides an excellent account of his work as a medical missionary at Gaziantep Hospital in Turkey. Further documentation is provided by diaries, writings, and collected material. These papers are complemented by the Merrill Isely Papers of YDSL Record Group No. 158. Isely was an American Board colleague of Dewey in Turkey.
Arrangement
I. Correspondence, 1898-1958
II. Writings, 1943-1946, n.d.
III. Collected Materials, 1931-1958
IV. Diaries, 1914-1938
V. Photographs, 1920-1921, n.d.
Missions -- Turkey; Missionaries; Dewey, Albert; American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions
- Correspondence, 1898-1958; Series I
  - Family Correspondence
    - To/ from parents of Albert Dewey, 1898-1915 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - To/ from parents of Albert Dewey, 1918-1931 (Box 1, Folder 2-34)
  - To/from siblings of AD
    - Alice Dewey, 1918-1928 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - David Dewey, 1918-1921 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Edward Dewey, 1918-1940 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Clarence Dewey, 1920-1924 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Various, 1930-1947 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - From others, 1923-1927 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - To/from children of AD
    - Letters, 1932-1940 Jul (Box 1, Folder 41-47)
    - Letters, 1940 Aug-1957 (Box 2, Folder 48-56)
  - Circular letters
    - Letters, 1921-1958 (Box 2, Folder 57-69)
  - General correspondence
    - Ansoy-Graham (Box 2, Folder 70)
    - Greene, Mrs. T. C. (Box 2, Folder 71)
    - Harris - Mouammer (Box 2, Folder 72)
    - Phelps, Teda Belle (Box 2, Folder 73)
    - Packard - Willard (Box 2, Folder 74)
    - first names only (Box 2, Folder 75)
- Writings, 1943-1946, n.d.; Series II
  - "A Review of some of the recent literature dealing with splenic enlargement" (Thesis submitted to Faculty of Graduate School of Medicine of University of Pennsylvania) (Box 2, Folder 76)
  - Annual meeting sermon, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 76)
  - Statement of reasons for my presence in Turkey, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 76)
  - Annual meeting sermon, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 76)
  - Miscellaneous, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 76)
- Collected Material, 1931-1958; Series III
  - Related to American Board mission in Turkey
    - Re. Gaziantep Hospital - brief history (Box 2, Folder 77)
    - Re. Gaziantep Hospital, Talas Clinic, American Hospital Istanbul (Box 2, Folder 78)
    - Re. Aintab Hospital (Gaziantep) (Box 2, Folder 79)
    - Re. American Board Mission in Turkey (Box 2, Folder 80)
    - Annual reports - Mission and Hospital, 1931-1949 (Box 2, Folder 81-83)
    - Annual reports - Mission and Hospital, 1950-1958 (Box 3, Folder 84-85)
  - Other
    - Re. Near East Relief (Box 3, Folder 86)
    - Re. earthquake in Turkey, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 87)
    - Travel (Box 3, Folder 88)
    - Turkey (Box 3, Folder 89)
- Personal Items and Memorabilia, 1914-1938; Series IV
  - Miscellaneous (Box 3, Folder 90)
  - Biographical documentation (Box 3, Folder 91)
- Diaries, 1914-1938; Series V
  - Albert Dewey, 1933-1935, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 92)
  - Albert Dewey, 1914-1917 (Box 3, Folder 93)
  - Elsie Dewey, 1929 (Box 3, Folder 94)
- Photographs, 1920-1921, n.d.; Series VI
  - Friends and colleagues (Box 3, Folder 95)
  - Travel in Near East, 1920-1921 (Box 3, Folder 96)
  - Family (Box 3, Folder 97)
  - Scenery and buildings (Box 3, Folder 98)
  - American Board Hospital and Mission buildings (Box 3, Folder 99)